The Philip Mackie Collection
The Philip Mackie Collection
- Literary Papers, 1952 - 1985; 1999; MAC/1; Solent University Library; Mackie Philip 1918-1985; 151 boxes (11.5 metres) plus scattered items
  - Good Girl, 1974; MAC/1/21; Solent University Library; 7 boxes plus scattered items
    Box 39: Rehearsal scripts (2 copies of episode 1 including side notes by Mackie; 2 copies of episode 6)
    Box 126: Letters from Peter Willes, Yorkshire TV, about the delivery of episodes.
    Box 146: Revised versions of rehearsal scripts (Feb-March 1974) for episodes 1-4 of Good Girl.
    Held in boxes 34-39; 126; 146
    IMDB page for Good Girl
  - Gossip, 1977; MAC/1/79; Solent University Library; Baker Terence 1939-1991; 10 items
    Papers relating to Gossip, a comedy series by Philip Mackie. The original idea and plot seem to have come from Terence Baker, whose name appears in one of the papers but not in subsequent and complete versions of the scripts. Mackie prepared Gossip in six episodes, but there is no evidence that it was ever produced.
    - A plot summary (6 pages) of Gossip by Terence Baker (1977)
    - 8 copies of scripts by Mackie relating to Gossip for episodes 1-6
    - A story outline by Mackie for Gossip including handwritten side notes
    - Letters to Terence Baker from Mackie relating to script changes and revisions
    Baker Terence 1939-1991
  - Harriette, 1974 - 1985; MAC/1/26; Solent University Library; Approximately 10 items
    Papers relating to Harriette, a screenplay by Mackie based on the memoirs of the courtesan Harriette Wilson, fl. 1805-1820. It appears never to have been produced.
    Two typewritten scripts, 145 pages and dated 25 Feb 1985.
    Correspondence with: Mike Wooller (BBC TV) [1974], James Cellan Jones (BBC TV) [1978], Verity Lambert (Thames TV) [1978], John Frankau [1980] discussing the possibility of a drama about Harriette Wilson.
    Held in boxes 40, 126, 127, 128.
  - Hurrah! The Flag, approximately 1956; MAC/1/88; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A complete and handwritten draft of Marching through Georgia - an earlier working title for Mackie's novel Hurrah! The Flag, published in 1957.
    Held in box 152
  - It Can't Last Forever, approximately 1970; MAC/1/45; Solent University Library; 1 item (125 pages)
    A script relating to It Can't Last Forever - a play in three acts by Philip Mackie. There is no external evidence to determine whether the play was ever produced.
    Held in box 86
  - Jemima Shore Investigates. A Splash of Red, 1982; MAC/1/53; Solent University Library; 3 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to A Splash of Red, a two-part dramatisation of the novel of the same name by Antonia Fraser, which was made for Thames Television and broadcast as part of the Jemima Shore Investigates series in 1983.
    Box 114: Six copies of scripts of A Splash of Red for episodes 1 and 2 -- Various letters between Philp Mackie and Tim Aspinall (Thames TV) regarding script revisions and filming schedules
    Box 115: Four copies of rehearsal scripts -- Various letters between Philp Mackie and Tim Aspinall (Thames TV) regarding script revisions
    New box 3: Two reading copies of revised scripts amended in July 1982
    Box 128: Correspondence with Tim Aspinall, including a request by Mackie to have his name taken off the production and replaced by the pseudonym Oscar Entwhistle. The letters also discuss Antonia Fraser's checking of the scripts and requests for changes.
    Held in boxes 114, 115, 128, and New box 3
    IMDB page for A Splash of Red
  - Le Dindon, 1965; MAC/1/36; Solent University Library; 1 box
    Papers relating to an adaptation, by Mackie, of Le Dindon by Georges Feydeau. The adaptation appears to have been prepared with a view to production in the theatre, but it is unclear if it was ever produced.
    Contents include two complete scripts with handwritten corrections, and a cover letter to Hugh Beaumont, dated 15 Feb 1965, relating to revisions of Act 1.
    Held in box 60
    Beaumont Binkie 1908-1973 Theatre manager and producer
  - Le Rouge et le Noir, 1978 - 1983; MAC/1/51; Solent University Library; 3 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to Le Rouge et le Noir, a dramatization, by Mackie, of the novel of the same name by Stendhal. Mackie's version also has variant titles: The Life of Julien Sorel and Julien Sorel. The dramatization appears never to have been produced.
    Box 110: Notes on locations and sets required. A collection of tourist pamphlets for France that may be part of Mackie's research for the adaptation.
    Box 112: Two typewritten bound copies of scripts and a notebook with Mackie's notes in French and English.
    Box 148: Two typewritten copies of scripts.
    New box 5: 5 copies of scripts of The Life of Julien Sorel and Julien Sorel for episodes 1-5
    Box 127: Correspondence between Mackie and Jonathan Powell and Betty Willingale (BBC TV) about casting and the script.
    Box 129: Correspondence from 1983.
    Held in boxes 110 & 112; 148; new box 5; 127 & 129.
  - Maigret and the Lady, approximately 1965; MAC/1/76; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Scripts for Maigret and the Lady, a play by Mackie based on the novel Maigret et la Vieille Dame by Georges Simenon. The play was performed in Manchester, Birmingham, Oxford, and London in 1965.In Mackie's typescript versions the play is called Maigret and the Old Lady.
    Held in box 133.
  - Maigret's Boyhood Friend, 1972; MAC/1/20; Solent University Library; 7 items
    Papers relating to Maigret's Boyhood Friend, a screenplay by Mackie of the novel by Georges Simenon. The screenplay appears never to have been produced; included are suggestions for alternative titles: Maigret and the Old Friend; Maigret's Old Friend.
    Contents
    Box 25: full draft and revised scripts and rewrites of selected sections.
    Box 133: three copies of scripts and revision notes related to Maigret's Boyhood Friend
    Box 143: A draft screenplay titled Maigret's Boyhood Friend - with handwritten changes and annotations. Script listed as "the property of David Paradine Films Ltd."
    Held in boxes 25, 133 & 143
  - Malice Aforethought, 1978; MAC/1/32; Solent University Library; 2 boxes
    Scripts relating to Malice Aforethought, a dramatization by Mackie for BBC TV of the novel of the same name by Anthony Berkeley Cox, using the pen name Francis Iles. The work was broadcast in four episodes in 1979.
    Box 50: Rehearsal scripts for episodes 1-4; 2 pages of revision notes
    Box 51: Rehearsal scripts for episodes 1, 3 and 4
    Box 82: Handwritten notes in notebook.
    Held in boxes 50, 51, 82.
    IMDB page for Malice Aforethought
  - Mr Rose, 1966 - 1967; MAC/1/34; Solent University Library; 7 boxes
    Camera and rehearsal scripts for Mr Rose, a 1967-68 Granada TV series created by Mackie.
    Held in boxes 53-59
    IMDB page for Mr. Rose
  - Nanking Road, 1982 - 1983; MAC/1/37; Solent University Library; 6 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to an adaptation, by Mackie, of Nanking Road by Vicki Baum. It appears never to have been produced, though letters indicate it was being worked on and looked at by C. P. Films, Manfred Durniok Productions, and CBS.
    Box 62: 4 revised second drafts of Nanking Road screenplay
    Box 63: 4 revised drafts of Nanking Road screenplay
    Box 64: 3 drafts plus various correspondence, including with John Pringle, CP Films
    Box 65: 3 copies of revised second drafts and 3 letters to John Pringle, CP Films, with notes on revisions.
    Box 66: 4 copies of revised drafts.
    Box 67: 4 revised first drafts of Nanking Road screenplay, some with handwritten annotations
    Box 128: Correspondence (1982).
    Box 129: Correspondence (1982-1983) with Jack Gold, with Stephen Smallwood and John Pringle, CP Films, and with Bob Markel, CBS, who gives very detailed notes on the draft scripts.
    Box 144: A revised second draft script.
    Held in boxes 62-67, 128, 129.
  - Napoleon and Love, 1972 - 1973; MAC/1/39; Solent University Library; 15 boxes
    Papers relating to Napoleon and Love, a historical drama written by Mackie and broadcast in 9 episodes by ITV in 1974.
    Box 68: Various original notes (most handwritten) relating the episodes (14 items)
    Box 69: Scripts for episodes 6 to 9
    Box 70: Scripts relating to episodes 1 to 4
    Box 71: Rehearsal scripts (reading copy) relating to episodes 1 and 2
    Box 72: Original and handwritten scripts relating to the various episodes
    Box 73: Scripts (first and revised versions) relating to episodes 1 to 4
    Box 74: Rehearsal scripts for episodes 3 and 6
    Box 75: Rehearsal scripts for episodes 4, 7, 8 & 9
    Box 76: Unbound copies of Napoleon and Love - a novel by Mackie (3 items)
    Box 77: Handwritten scripts on notebooks relating to the various episodes
    Box 78: Unbound copy of Napoleon and Love - a novel by Mackie
    Box 79: Rehearsal scripts for episodes 3, 5, 6 & 8
    Box 80: Handwritten scripts on notebooks relating to the various episodes
    Box 126: Correspondence relating to a novelization of Napoleon and Love
    Box 140: Four copies of scripts (some with handwritten corrections) relating to episodes 8 and 9
    Box 144: Several press clippings including from the Daily Mail (19 Feb 1974; 13 March 1974), an article from The Daily Telegraph Magazine (1 March 1974), and a black and white photograph probably depicting four members of the cast.
    Held in boxes 68-80; 126; 140, 144
    IMDB page for Napoleon and Love
  - Nell!, 1964; 1970; MAC/1/40; Solent University Library; Worth Johnny 1931-2021 Songwriter; 1 box
    Papers relating to Nell!, a musical based on the life of Nell Gwynne. The story was written by Philip Mackie in collaboration with Johnny Worth, who wrote the music and lyrics. It was performed at the Richmond Theatre, London, in April 1970.
    Includes:
    An (apparently) early version written entirely by Johnny Worth, which was returned to Mackie by agent Richard Gregson in December 1964 with a letter indicating interest in the work.
    A typewritten revision of the book by Mackie.
    A script with a return slip from the Richmond Theatre; this script contains lots of revisions, and a handwritten note indicating the date of rehearsals and opening.
    Held in box 81
    Worth Johnny 1931-2021 Songwriter
  - Open House, 1957; MAC/1/87; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Two scripts for Mackie's Open House - a farce in three acts, prepared for Perth Theatre.
    Held in box 142
  - Pamela, or, Virtue Rewarded, 1982 - 1985; MAC/1/46; Solent University Library; 5 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to Pamela or Virtue Rewarded, a dramatization, by Mackie, of the novel by Samuel Richardson. The dramatization appears never to have been produced although it was evidently in the advanced stages of production with Thames TV.
    Contents include various versions of scripts, including some produced by Thames TV, one of which has dates set for recording in April-July 1985. There is correspondence between Mackie and director Peter Duguid and Lloyd Shirley, Thames TV, in which they discuss revisions and casting. And correspondence between Mackie and Colin Shindler (BBC TV) about the possibility of producing the work.
    Held in boxes 91-95, 128-130.
  - Paris 1900, 1963 - 1964; MAC/1/47; Solent University Library; 6 boxes
    Papers relating to Paris 1900, a 1964 Granada TV series consisting of versions of Georges Feydeau's farces, translated and adapted by Mackie.
    Episode list:
    The Ribadier System
    Fashions for Ladies
    The Lambert Affair
    Half a Husband
    The Ribbon
    The Luck of the Game
    Box 91: A script of The Ribadier System.
    Box 96: 9 copies of original drafts and revisions relating to the six parts in the series
    Box 97: 4 copies of rehearsal scripts for parts 3-6
    Box 98: 4 copies of rehearsal scripts for parts 2-5
    Box 131B: 1 copy of rehearsal script for the episode The Luck of the Game
    Box 134: 2 copies of rehearsal script for the episodes 1 and 2
    Held in boxes 91, 96-98, 131B, 134
    IMDB page for Paris 1900
  - Praying Mantis, 1981 - 1982; MAC/1/48; Solent University Library; 2 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to Praying mantis, a 1982 Channel 4 TV dramatization of the novel Les Mantes Religieuses by Hubert Monteilhet.
    Box 101:
    Revised versions for part 1 and 2 Praying mantis
    Press reviews for Praying mantis
    A photocopy of The Praying Mantises - translated from the French by Richard Howard - published in 1962, 159 pages
    Correspondence with Ian Warren and Jack Gold about script revisions
    Box 102:
    5 copies of scripts for parts 1 and 2
    Script revisions and other notes
    Correspondence with Ian Warren and Jack Gold.
    Held in boxes 101, 102, 128.
    IMDB page for Praying Mantis
  - Raffles, 1975 - 1977; MAC/1/2; Solent University Library; West Gilian; 8 boxes
    Papers relating to Raffles, a Yorkshire Television series (1977, with a pilot in 1975) adapted by Mackie from the stories of E. W. Hornung.
    Camera scripts and rehearsal scripts for several episodes, including some for a 'new series' that was never made.
    Correspondence between Mackie and Jacky Stoller regarding script changes, transmission order, etc.
    1 production schedule for Raffles
    2 copies of script changes.
    Handwritten notes in notebook in box 82.
    Correspondence from and an unpublished article on Raffles by Gilian West, lecturer in English at the University of Hull.
    An article, Raffles and Bunny, written by Mackie and dated 20 January 1977.
    Correspondence relating to the novelization of the series by Dulan Barber (David Fletcher).
    Held in boxes 82, 99-100, 105-107, 109, 126 and 139.
    IMDB page for Raffles
    Stoller Jacky; West Gilian
  - Red Letter Day. The Retirement, or, Last Orders, 1974; MAC/1/7; Solent University Library; 1 item
    Script for Red Letter Day. The Retirement (alternative title: Last Orders ) by Mackie. The script was probably prepared for the Granada TV anthology series Red Letter Day (1976). It appears, however, that this episode was never made.
    Held in box 2
    IMDB page for Red Letter Day [related work]
  - Saki, 1962; MAC/1/4; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Two typewritten scripts for Saki, a 1962 Granada TV series featuring adaptations, by Mackie, of the works of Saki.
    Held in box 46.
    IMDB page for Saki
  - Shades of Greene, 1974 - 1975; MAC/1/5; Solent University Library; 3 boxes
    Papers relating to two episodes of Shades of Greene, a 1975-76 Thames TV series dramatizing short stories of Graham Greene.
    Various scripts (drafts, camera scripts, and rehearsal scripts) for two episodes dramatized by Mackie, A Drive in the Country and Cheap in August.
    4 typewritten (some with duplicate copies) and 1 handwritten correspondence between Mackie and Alan Cooke - all relating to script changes and revisions; (some with marginal notes by Mackie).
    2 handwritten pages of pre-production outlines for Cheap in August.
    Letter (dated 18 September [1975]) from Virginia McKenna, who starred in Cheap in August, praising the writing.
    Held in boxes 1, 104, and 111
    IMDB page for Shades of Greene
    Cooke Alan 1926-1994 Film director
  - Snow White, approximately 1985; MAC/1/38; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Papers relating to Snow White, a proposed screenplay by Mackie, based on the fairy tale; it appears never to have been made.
    Two typewritten copies of a detailed treatment (40 pages).
    Several pages of notes on setting, characters etc.
    Held in box 25 and 130.
  - Someone on the Line, or, Wrong Number, 1954; MAC/1/71; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Scripts for Someone on the Line, Mackie's dramatization of Norman Edwards' novel Wrong Number. One script is a rehearsal script, which gives the date of transmission as Tuesday, 28 September. The other appears to be an earlier draft, is titled Wrong Number, and there is a note saying it should be returned to Mr Brandon Acton-Bond at the BBC. Acton-Bond is listed as the producer on the other script. There is no external evidence for the script's production, but it does appear to have gone ahead.
    Held in box 136
  - Super-Priority, 1952; MAC/1/77; Solent University Library; 1 item
    Shooting script for Super-Priority, to be made at Cinetone Studios Amsterdam. The work is described as a 'half-hour TV film', but appears to be a film of the kind made for the Ministry of Information, Films Division, for whom Mackie worked. There is no evidence to indicate whether it was produced, however.
    Held in box 137.
  - The Anti-Death League, MAC/1/13; Solent University Library; Amis Kingsley 1922-1995; 1 box plus scattered items
    Papers relating to a dramatization by Mackie of the Kingsley Amis novel The Anti-Death League. It seems the dramatization was never produced.
    Scripts for episodes 1-4 of The Anti-Death League.
    Correspondence between Mackie and Cliff Owen (1977-1985), director, with script amendments, and an updated scenario for 'Operation Apollo' by Kingsley Amis.
    Correspondence (1978-1983) between Mackie and various TV executives exploring the possibility of producing the drama.
    Mainly held in box 8. There is correspondence in boxes 17, 127, 128, 129.
    Amis Kingsley 1922-1995
  - The Big Killing, approximately 1962; MAC/1/60; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Scripts for The Big Killing, a play by Philip Mackie. The play seems to have been first produced in a theatre in 1962. There were subsequent Australian (1965) and French ( Meurtre à crédit, 1974) TV adaptations.
    Held in box 131B, 150; Unnumbered box (Mackie Spare Box #1)
    IMDB page for The Big Killing [Related work].
    Meurtre à crédit [Related work].
  - The Caesars, 1965 - 1969; MAC/1/89; Solent University Library; Several item
    Papers relating to The Caesars a 1968 Granada TV series written by Mackie.
    Box 104: Memo to 'members of the programme committtee', 10 December 1964, proposing a series dealing with the Caesars. -- Several copies of an outline for a series of 13 one-hour programmes (dated from 1965 to 1969), which take the story up to AD69, further than the series reached. -- Partial, handwritten notes detailing how the series should be run, including costings (dated 1965).
    Box 152: Handwritten notes in a notebook detailing the chronology up to the accession of Tiberius and onwards as well as what appears to be an outline/synopses.
    Box 143: Notes in a notebook on turning The Caesars into a stage play.
    Held in boxes 104, 143 and 152
    IMDB page for The Caesars
  - The Chairman, 1975 - 1976; MAC/1/61; Solent University Library; approximately 14 items
    Papers relating to The Chairman, a play by Philip Mackie based on his TV series, The Organization. The Chairman was published in 1976 and probably the play was first produced in the same year.
    Scripts, some with have handwritten annotations and revisions.
    Correspondence with Hazel Vincent Wallace, of the Thorndike Theatre, suggesting that the The Organization be turned into a play and performed at the Thorndike (May 1975).
    Programme from a run at the Globe Theatre.
    Letter from David Firth, who played David Pershore in the play, dated 26 May 1976.
    Held in boxes 104; 126; 131B; 146; 150.
  - The Changeling, 1964; MAC/1/29; Solent University Library; 2 items
    Typewritten scripts for a dramatization of Thomas Middleton and William Rowley's The Changeling, which was broadcast as part of ITV's Play of the Week on 4 January 1965.
    Held in boxes 42 & 134
    IMDB page for The Changeling
  - The Cleopatras, 1977 - 1983; MAC/1/16; Solent University Library; Learner R. C. M. University professor; 9 boxes plus scattered items
    Papers relating to The Cleopatras, a 1983 BBC TV series in eight episodes, written by Philip Mackie, and to the accompanying novel, published by the BBC in 1983.
    Draft and rehearsal scripts for each episode [Boxes 11-17].
    Correspondence (with Graeme McDonald and William Slater, both at BBC Drama and TV) and notes related to the initiation of The Cleopatras project, 1980 [Box 17].
    2 cast lists [Box 17].
    Correspondence discussing script amendments with Guy Slater, BBC TV [Box 17]
    3 script excerpts with changes [Box 17]
    'The Cleopatras: an historical outline' written by R. C. M. Learner, January 1977 [Box 17]
    A 49 page typewritten document entitled: Cleopatra: introduction and episode one [Box 17]
    Correspondence relating to the production of the series, and to the role of R. C. M. Leaner in its development (1980-1982) [Box 128].
    Correspondence with Guy Slater and David Reid, BBC TV, (1982-1983) [Box 129].
    Draft versions of the novelization of the series by Philip Mackie [Boxes 18-19].
    Correspondence relating to the production of the novel (1981-1982) [Box 128].
    Held in boxes 11-19, and 128 & 129.
    IMDB page for The Cleopatras
    Learner R. C. M. University professor; Slater Guy b 1941
  - The Edgar Wallace Mysteries, 1960 - 1962; MAC/1/72; Solent University Library; 1 box
    Papers relating to episodes of The Edgar Wallace Mysteries, a second-feature film series mainly produced at Merton Park Studios for Anglo-Amalgamated between 1960 and 1965, which dramatized stories by Edgar Wallace.
    Correspondence between Mackie and Jack Greenwood, of Anglo-Guild Productions, relating to script and story changes for several of the films listed below.
    Outlines for several films: The Man at the Carlton Tower (1961); The Clue of the Siver Key (1961); Number Six (1962); The Clue of the Twisted Candle (1960).
    Scripts for several films: The Clue of the Twisted Candle (1960); The £20,000 Kiss (1962); Number Six (1962).
    Held in boxes 137 & 149.
    IMDB page for The Edgar Wallace Mystery series
  - The Editors, 1960; MAC/1/64; Solent University Library; 1 item
    A script for The Editors, a discussion programme about standards in the British press, which was made by Granada TV on 20 July 1960. No date of transmission has been found. The script includes verbatim or suggested comments for the chairman, Lord Birkett, and contributors - editors of various national newspapers and Members of Parliament. Mackie is listed as a producer.
    Held in box 124
  - The Girl at the Next Table [Musical], 1963 - 1964; MAC/1/74; Solent University Library; Jaques Jimmy Lyricist; Gascoigne Bamber; Carmichael Ian 1920-2010; More Julian 1928-2010; 1 box
    Papers relating to The Girl at the Next Table, a musical version of the 1957 BBC TV programme written by Philip Mackie. This version appears to have been in preparation for the stage in 1963-64, but there is no external information to confirm if this version was ever produced.
    Several draft books for the musical with handwritten annotations; an apparently later version of the books includes early lyrics by Jimmy Jaques.
    Correspondence between Mackie and Ian Carmichael (who was to play the lead role), Bamber Gascoigne, and Julian More (both of whom were potential lyricists).
    A list of scenes, a list of songs, and some lyrics.
    Held in box 132.
    Jaques Jimmy Lyricist; Gascoigne Bamber; Carmichael Ian 1920-2010; More Julian 1928-2010
  - The Girl at the Next Table [Play], approximately 1957; MAC/1/75; Solent University Library; 3 item
    Scripts for The Girl at the Next Table, a theatrical version of the 1957 BBC TV programme of the same name, written by Philip Mackie. Two scripts are handwritten; the third is typed and bound.
    Held in boxes 33 and 132
  - The Girl at the Next Table [TV], approximately 1957; MAC/1/25; Solent University Library; 3 items
    Papers relating to The Girl at the Next Table, a teleplay by Mackie broadcast as part of the BBC series Sunday-Night Theatre in 1957.